Two years ago, I have to say there was no problem.
قبل عامين، يجب أن أقول بأنه لم يكن هناك مشكل.
Two years ago, I knew exactly what an icon looked like.
قبل عامين، عرفتُ تماما كيف تبدو الأيقونة.
It looks like this.
إنها تشبه هذه.
Everybody's icon, but also the default position
كانت أيقونة بالنسبة للجميع، بل أيضا بمثابة
of a curator of Italian Renaissance paintings, which I was then.
الوصي على لوحات عصر النهضة الإيطالية، وهو المنصب الذي كنت أشغله حين ذاك.
And in a way, this is also another default selection.
وعلى نحو ما، هذه أيضا باقة بديهية.
Leonardo da Vinci's exquisitely soulful image
صورة ليونارد دا فينشي الرائعة والمفعمة بالحياة
of the "Lady with an Ermine."
"للسيدة التي ترتدي فرو القاقم."
And I use that word, soulful, deliberately.
عندما أقول مفعمة بالحياة، فإنني تعمدت استخدام هذه العبارة.
Or then there's this, or rather these:
وإلا سيكون هنالك الآتي:
the two versions of Leonardo's "Virgin of the Rocks"
"عذراء الصخور" لليوناردو بنسختيها المختلفتين
that were about to come together in London for the very first time.
كانتا ستصدران معًا في لندن للمرة الأولى
In the exhibition that I was then in the absolute throes of organizing.
في المعرض الذي كنت حينها في موقع المسؤولية عن تنظيمه.
I was literally up to my eyes in Leonardo,
كنت كثير الانشغال بليوناردو
and I had been for three years.
لفترة ثلاثة سنوات.
So, he was occupying every part of my brain.
لقد كان يشغل كل جزء من عقلي.
Leonardo had taught me, during that three years,
علمني ليوناردو خلال ثلك الأعوام الثلاثة
about what a picture can do.
ما بإمكان لوحة القيام به.
About taking you from your own material world into a spiritual world.
بإمكانها أن تأخذك من عالمك المادي إلى عالم روحاني.
He said, actually, that he believed the job of the painter
في الحقيقة لقد كان يعتقد أنّ عمل الفنان كان
was to paint everything that was visible and invisible in the universe.
أن يرسم كل شي مرئي وغير مرئي في الكون
That's a huge task. And yet, somehow he achieves it.
هذه مهمة كبيرة، لكنه بطريقة ما أنجزها.
He shows us, I think, the human soul.
هو يرينا، حسب رأيي، الروح البشرية.
He shows us the capacity of ourselves
هو يرينا مقدراتنا الشخصية
to move into a spiritual realm.
لنتحرك في حقل الروحانيات.
To see a vision of the universe that's more perfect than our own.
لنرى صورة للكون أكثر كمالًا من تصورنا.
To see God's own plan, in some sense.
لنرى خطة الرب بإدراك معين.
So this, in a sense, was really what I believed an icon was.
وهذا كان نوعا ما تعريفي للأيقونة.
At about that time, I started talking to Tom Campbell,
في تلك الفترة كنت قد بدأت التحدث مع توم كامبل،
director here of the Metropolitan Museum,
مخرج هنا في متحف المتروبوليان
about what my next move might be.
عن خطوتي القادمة.
The move, in fact, back to an earlier life,
خطوة اتخذتها في حياتي سابقًا،
one I'd begun at the British Museum,
كنت قد بدأتها في المتحف البريطاني
back to the world of three dimensions --
عودة إلى العالم الثلاثي الأبعاد --
of sculpture and of decorative arts --
من تماثيل وفنون زخرفية --
to take over the department of European sculpture and decorative arts, here at the Met.
لتولّي قسم المنحوتات الأوروبية والفنون الزخرفية، هنا في متحف المتروبوليان.
But it was an incredibly busy time.
لكن وقتي كان مشغولا جدّا.
All the conversations were done at very peculiar times of the day --
كل الحوارات كانت تحدث في أوقات غريبة من اليوم --
over the phone.
عبر الهاتف.
In the end, I accepted the job
في النهاية، قبلت العمل
without actually having been here.
دون حتّى زيارة المكان.
Again, I'd been there a couple of years before,
أذكّركم أنّني قد زرته سابقًا منذ بضعة سنوات،
but on that particular visit.
لكن في زيارة خاصة.
So, it was just before the time that the Leonardo show was due to open
إذن لقد حدث الأمر مباشرة قبل افتتاح معرض ليوناردو،
when I finally made it back to the Met, to New York,
عندما عدت إلى المتروبوليان بنيويورك.
to see my new domain.
لأرى ميداني الجديد.
To see what European sculpture and decorative arts looked like,
لأرى شكل المنحوتات الأوروبية والزخارف الفنية،
beyond those Renaissance collections with which I was so already familiar.
بعيدًا عن مجموعات عهد النهضة التي اعتدت عليها.
And I thought, on that very first day, I better tour the galleries.
وفكّرت منذ اليوم الأول أنّه من الأفضل زيارة كلّ الأروقة
Fifty-seven of these galleries --
التي يبلغ عددها 57 --
like 57 varieties of baked beans, I believe.
مثل 57 نوعــًا من أنواع الفاصوليا.
I walked through and I started in my comfort zone in the Italian Renaissance.
ذهبت في جولة وبدأت في منطقة ارتياحي، النهضة الإيطالية.
And then I moved gradually around,
بعدها ذهبت تدريجيًا إلى ما أبعد،
feeling a little lost sometimes.
شعرت بأنني ضائع في بعض الأحيان.
My head, also still full of the Leonardo exhibition
مازال عقلي مشغولًا بمعرض ليوناردو
that was about to open, and I came across this.
الذي لم يكن تم افتتاحه بعد، فصادفت هذا.
And I thought to myself: What the hell have I done?
وفكرت: ما الكارثة التي قمت بها؟
There was absolutely no connection in my mind
لم يكن هنالك أي ارتباط في بالي
at all and, in fact, if there was any emotion going on,
مطلقًا، في الحقيقة وحتّى لو كانت هنالك بعض المشاعر
it was a kind of repulsion.
فقد كانت مشاعر تمرد.
This object felt utterly and completely alien.
هذا التمثال بدا لي غريبا تماما،
Silly at a level that I hadn't yet understood silliness to be.
سخيف إلى درجة لم أفهم معها معنى السخف.
And then it was made worse --
وبعدها أصبح شعوري أسوأ
there were two of them.
كان هنالك اثنان منهما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I started thinking about why it was, in fact,
وبدأت بالتفكير في سبب،
that I disliked this object so much.
كرهي الشديد لهذا التمثال.
What was the anatomy of my distaste?
ما كانت طبيعة نفوري منه؟
Well, so much gold, so vulgar.
هناك الكثير من الذهب، مبتذل جدًا
You know, so nouveau riche, frankly.
يبدو كأسلوب مستجدي الثراء، بصدق.
Leonardo himself had preached against the use of gold,
ليوناردو نفسه نصح بعدم استخدام الذهب،
so it was absolutely anathema at that moment.
لقد كان الأمر أشبه بلعنة في ذلك الوقت.
And then there's little pretty sprigs of flowers everywhere. (Laughter)
وهناك أغصان صغيرة من الزهور في كلّ مكان. (ضحك)
And finally, that pink. That damned pink.
وأخيرًا، اللون الوردي. ذلك اللون الوردي الملعون.
It's such an extraordinarily artificial color.
لقد كان يبدو لونا اصطناعيا جدّا.
I mean, it's a color that I can't think of anything that you actually see in nature,
لا يمكنني التفكير في أي شيء تراه في الطبيعة
that looks that shade.
يبدو بهذا اللون.
The object even has its own tutu. (Laughter)
بل إن لهذا الثمثال توتو الخاص به. (ضحك)
This little flouncy, spangly, bottomy bit
هذا الطرف النهائي الصغير اللامع
that sits at the bottom of the vase.
الذي يجلس في الجزء السفلي من المزهرية.
It reminded me, in an odd kind of way,
ذكرني، بطريقة غريبة،
of my niece's fifth birthday party.
بحفلة عيد الميلاد الخامس لابنة أخي.
Where all the little girls would come either as a princess or a fairy.
حيث أن جميع الفتيات الصغيرات تأتين مرتديات ملابس جنية أو أميرة.
There was one who would come as a fairy princess.
أحدهن كانت تأتي مرتدية كأميرة جنية.
You should have seen the looks.
كان عليكم رؤية ردّة فعل الآخرين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I realize that this object was in my mind,
وأنا أدرك أن هذا التمثال في رأيي،
born from the same mind, from the same womb,
ولد من العقل نفسه، من نفس الرحم،
practically, as Barbie Ballerina. (Laughter)
عمليًا، كباربي راقصة باليه. (ضحك)
And then there's the elephants. (Laughter)
ومن ثم هناك الفيلة.
Those extraordinary elephants
تلك الفيلة غير عادية
with their little, sort of strange, sinister expressions
بتعابيرها الغريبة والشريرة نوعا ما،
and Greta Garbo eyelashes, with these golden tusks and so on.
ورموش غريتا غاربو، وهذه الأنياب الذهبية وهلم جرا.
I realized this was an elephant that had
أدركت أن هذا كان فيلًا لم يكن
absolutely nothing to do with a majestic march across the Serengeti.
له دخل على الإطلاق بمسيرة مهيبة عبر سيرنغيتي.
It was a Dumbo nightmare. (Laughter)
كان كابوس دومبو. (ضحك)
But something more profound was happening as well.
ولكن كان يحدث شيء أكثر عمقًا، كذلك.
These objects, it seemed to me,
هذه التماثيل، بدت بالنسبة لي،
were quintessentially the kind that I and my liberal left friends in London
كانت بشكل أساسي النوع الذي كنا وأصدقائي الليبراليين اليساريين في لندن
had always seen as summing up
دومًا نراه على أنه إجمال
something deplorable about the French aristocracy
لشيء مؤسف عن الأرستقراطية الفرنسية
in the 18th century.
في القرن الثامن عشر.
The label had told me that these pieces were made
التسمية أوحت لي بأن هذه القطع تم صناعتها
by the Sèvres Manufactory,
بمصنع "سفرس"،
made of porcelain in the late 1750s,
مصنوعة من الخزف في أواخر الخمسينات من القرن الثامن عشر،
and designed by a designer called Jean-Claude Duplessis,
والمصممة بواسطة مصمم يدعى جان-كلود دوبليسيس،
actually somebody of extraordinary distinction
فعلًا شخص ما متميز بشكل استثنائي
as I later learned.
كما علمت فيما بعد.
But for me, they summed up a kind of,
ولكن بالنسبة لي، لخصوا نوعًا من،
that sort of sheer uselessness of the aristocracy
ذلك النوع من عدمية فائدة تلك للطبقة الأرستقراطية
in the 18th century.
في القرن الثامن عشر.
I and my colleagues had always thought
لقد اعتقدت دائمًا أنا وزملائي
that these objects, in way, summed up the idea of,
بأن هذه التماثيل، بشكل من الأشكال، لخصت الفكرة،
you know -- no wonder there was a revolution.
كما تعلمون--لا عجب أن كانت هناك ثورة.
Or, indeed, thank God there was a revolution.
أو، في الواقع، الحمد لله أن كانت هناك ثورة.
There was a sort of idea really, that,
وكان هناك حقًا نوع من فكرة، أن،
if you owned a vase like this,
أنك إذا امتلكت مزهرية مثل هذه،
then there was really only one fate possible.
إذن فهناك بالفعل مصير واحد ممكن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, there I was -- in a sort of paroxysm of horror.
لذا، كنت هناك- في شيء من ذروة الرعب.
But I took the job and I went on looking at these vases.
ولكن أخذت الوظيفة وأكلمت النظر إلى هذه المزهريات.
I sort of had to because they're on a through route in the Met.
نوعًا ما كان عليّ فعل ذلك لأنها في طريق على طول المتروبوليان.
So, almost anywhere I went, there they were.
لذا، ففي كل مكان ذهبت إليه تقريبًا، كانت هناك.
They had this kind of odd sort of fascination,
كان لديهم هذا النوع من الصنف الغريب من السحر،
like a car accident.
مثل حادث سيارة.
Where I couldn't stop looking.
حيث لم أستطع أن أتوقف عن النظر.
And as I did so, I started thinking:
وكلما فعلت ذلك، بدأت في التفكير:
Well, what are we actually looking at here?
حسنا، ما الذي ننظر إليه هنا؟
And what I started with was understanding this
وما بدأت به كان فهم هذه
as really a supreme piece of design.
على أنها حقًا قطعة مميزة في التصميم.
It took me a little time.
استغرق مني الكثير من الوقت.
But, that tutu for example --
ولكن، تلك الـ "توتو" على سبيل المثال-
actually, this is a piece that does dance in its own way.
في الواقع، هذه هي القطعة التي ترقص على طريقتها الخاصة.
It has an extraordinary lightness
إنها تملك نورًا لا مثيل له
and yet, it is also amazing balanced.
ومع ذلك، فإنها أيضا متوازنة إلى الحد الذي يثير الدهشة.
It has these kinds of sculptural ingredients.
إنها تملك هذه الأنواع من العناصر المنقوشة.
And then the play between --
ومن ثم اللعب بين-
actually really quite carefully disposed color and gilding, and the sculptural surface,
في الحقيقة اللون المتدرج بعناية وطلاء بالذهب والسطح المنقوش
is really rather remarkable.
هي فعلًا رائعة للغاية.
And then I realized that this piece went into the kiln
وأدركت بعد ذلك أن هذه القطعة ذهبت إلى الفرن
four times, at least four times in order to arrive at this.
أربع مرات، على الأقل أربع مرات من أجل أن تصل لهذه الحالة.
How many moments for accident can you think of
كم عدد اللحظات التي تستطيع أن تفكر بها للحادث
that could have happened to this piece?
الذي يمكن أن تكون تعرضت له هذه القطعة؟
And then remember, not just one, but two.
ومن ثم تذكر، ليست واحدةً فقط، بل اثنتين.
So he's having to arrive at two exactly matched
إذن هو عليه التوصل إلى مزهريتين متطابقتين تمامًا
vases of this kind.
من هذا النوع.
And then this question of uselessness.
ومن ثم هذا السؤال لا فائدة منه.
Well actually, the end of the trunks were originally candle holders.
حسنًا في الواقع، كانت نهاية الخراطيم في الأصل شمعدانات.
So what you would have had were candles on either side.
لذا ما كنت ستملكه هو شموع على الجانبين.
Imagine that effect of candlelight on that surface.
تخيل تأثير ضوء الشموع على ذلك السطح.
On the slightly uneven pink, on the beautiful gold.
على الوردي المتموج، على الذهبي الجميل.
It would have glittered in an interior,
سيكون قد تلألأ في الديكور،
a little like a little firework.
قليلًا كألعاب نارية صغيرة.
And at that point, actually, a firework went off in my brain.
وفي تلك اللحظة، في الواقع، الألعاب النارية انفجرت في ذهني.
Somebody reminded me that, that word 'fancy' --
شخص ما ذكرني بأن، أن كلمة فانسي (نزوة)
which in a sense for me, encapsulated this object --
والتي لها مدلولها عندي، غلفت هذا التمثال-
actually comes from the same root as the word 'fantasy.'
في الواقع تأتي من نفس الجذر لكلمة فانتزي (وهم).
And that what this object was just as much in a way,
وهذا ما كان عليه هذا التمثال بنفس القدر بطريقة ما،
in its own way, as a Leonardo da Vinci painting,
بطريقتها الخاصة، كلوحة ليوناردو دا فينشي،
is a portal to somewhere else.
بوابة إلى مكان آخر.
This is an object of the imagination.
هذا التمثال من الخيال.
If you think about the mad 18th-century operas of the time -- set in the Orient.
إذا كنت تفكر في أوبرات القرن الثامن عشر المجنونة في ذلك الزمان-- والتي كانت في دول المشرق.
If you think about divans and perhaps even opium-induced visions of pink elephants,
إذا كنت تفكر في دواوين الشعر ولربما في تصورات الأفيال الوردية التي يسببها الأفيون
then at that point, this object starts to make sense.
عند تلك اللحظة، يبدأ يتكون لهذا التمثال معنى.
This is an object which is all about escapism.
هذا التمثال الذي يتحدث بأكمله عن الهروب من الواقع.
It's about an escapism that happens --
حول الهروب من الواقع الذي يحدث-
that the aristocracy in France sought
والذي سعى إليه النبلاء في فرنسا
very deliberately
بإصرار شديد
to distinguish themselves from ordinary people.
ليميزو أنفسهم عن الناس العاديين.
It's not an escapism that
إنه ليس هروبًا من الواقع قد
we feel particularly happy with today, however.
يشعرنا بالسعادة اليوم، على أية حال.
And again, going on thinking about this,
ومرة أخرى، نستمر بالتفكير حول هذا الموضوع،
I realize that in a way we're all victims
أدرك أننا جميعًا بطريقة ما ضحايا
of a certain kind of tyranny
لنوع معين من الطغيان
of the triumph of modernism
لانتصار الحداثة
whereby form and function in an object
الذي من خلاله يتوجب على شكل ووظيفة التمثال
have to follow one another, or are deemed to do so.
أن يتبع أحدهما الآخر، أو أن مصيرهما أن يفعلا ذلك.
And the extraneous ornament is seen as really,
أما الزخرفة منقطعة النظير فتتم رؤيتها على أنها حقيقة
essentially, criminal.
وبشكل أساسي، مجرمة.
It's a triumph, in a way, of bourgeois values rather than aristocratic ones.
إنها انتصار، بطريقة ما، للقيم البرجوازية بدلًا من تلك الأرستقراطية.
And that seems fine.
ويبدو أن ذلك أمرا جيدا.
Except for the fact that it becomes a kind of sequestration of imagination.
باستثناء حقيقة أنها تصبح نوعًا من تنحية الخيال.
So just as in the 20th century, so many people
لذلك كما هو الحال في القرن العشرين، الكثير من الناس
had the idea that their faith
امتلكوا فكرة أن إيمانهم
took place on the Sabbath day,
جرى في يوم السبت،
and the rest of their lives --
وبقية حياتهم-
their lives of washing machines and orthodontics --
حياتهم من الغسالات وتقويم الأسنان-
took place on another day.
جرت في يوم آخر.
Then, I think we've started doing the same.
ثم، أعتقد بأننا قد بدأنا بالقيام بنفس الشيء.
We've allowed ourselves to
لقد سمحنا لأنفسنا بأن
lead our fantasy lives in front of screens.
نقود حياتنا الخيالية أمام الشاشات.
In the dark of the cinema, with the television in the corner of the room.
في ظلمات السينما والتلفزيون في ركن الغرفة.
We've eliminated, in a sense, that constant
لقد تخلصنا، نوعًا ما، من ذلك
of the imagination that these vases represented in people's lives.
الثبات في التصور بأن المزهريات ممثلة في حياة الناس.
So maybe it's time we got this back a little.
ولذلك ربما حان الوقت لأن نعيد هذا قليلًا.
I think it's beginning to happen.
أعتقد أن هذا بدأ يحدث.
In London, for example,
في لندن، على سبيل المثال،
with these extraordinary buildings
مع هذه المباني الرائعة
that have been appearing over the last few years.
التي قد بدأت بالظهور خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية.
Redolent, in a sense, of science fiction,
تذكرنا، نوعًا ما، بالخيال العلمي،
turning London into a kind of fantasy playground.
تحول لندن إلى نوع ما من ملاهي الأحلام.
It's actually amazing to look out of a high building nowadays there.
ومن المدهش فعلا أن ننظر خارج بناية عالية في الوقت الحاضر هناك.
But even then, there's a resistance.
وحتى في ذلك الوقت، هناك مقاومة.
London has called these buildings the Gherkin, the Shard, the Walkie Talkie --
لقد أسمت لندن هذه المباني ب ـ غيركين، شارد، ووكي توكي-
bringing these soaring buildings down to Earth.
تجلب هذه المباني الشاهقة إلى الأرض.
There's an idea that we don't want these
وهناك فكرة بأننا لا نريد هذه
anxious-making, imaginative journeys to happen in our daily lives.
الرحلات الخيالية، المعدة بعناية، أن تحدث في حياتنا اليومية.
I feel lucky in a way,
أشعر بأنني محظوظ بطريقة ما،
I've encountered this object.
بمقابلة هذا التمثال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I found him on the Internet when I was looking up a reference.
لقد وجدته على الإنترنت بينما كنت أبحث عن مرجع.
And there he was.
كان هناك.
And unlike the pink elephant vase,
وعلى عكس مزهرية الفيل الوردي،
this was a kind of love at first sight.
كان هذا نوعًا من الحب من أول نظرة.
In fact, reader, I married him. I bought him.
وفي الواقع، أيها المستمعون، تزوجت منه. اشتريته.
And he now adorns my office.
وهو الآن يزين مكتبي.
He's a Staffordshire figure made in the middle of the 19th century.
هو ثمثال من الخزف الستافوردشيريّ صنع في منتصف القرن التاسع عشر.
He represents the actor, Edmund Kean, playing Shakespeare's Richard III.
إنه يمثل الممثل، إدموند كين، الذي يمثل دور ريتشارد الثالث في إحدى مسرحيات شكسبير.
And it's based, actually, on a more elevated piece of porcelain.
وهو يستند، في الواقع، إلى قطعة من الخزف بارزة بشكل أكبر.
So I loved, on an art historical level,
لذا أحببت ذلك، على المستوى التاريخي للفن،
I loved that layered quality that he has.
أحببت تلك الجودة التي يمتلكها على صعيد الطبقات.
But more than that, I love him.
ولكن أكثر من ذلك، أحببته.
In a way that I think would have been impossible
بطريقة أعتقد أنها كانت مستحيلة
without the pink Sèvres vase in my Leonardo days.
لولا مزهرية السيرفس الوردي أيام ليوناردو الخاصة بي.
I love his orange and pink breeches.
أحب بنطاله القصير الوردي والبرتقالي.
I love the fact that he seems to be going off to war,
أحب حقيقة أنه يبدو خارجًا إلى الحرب،
having just finished the washing up. (Laughter)
وقد انتهى لتوه من الغسيل. (ضحك)
He seems also to have forgotten his sword.
ويبدو أنه أيضًا قد نسي سيفه.
I love his pink little cheeks, his munchkin energy.
أحب خدوده الوردية الصغيرة، طاقة المنشكن خاصته.
In a way, he's become my sort of alter ego.
بطريقة ما، انه قد أصبح صنفي من الأنا الثانية.
He's, I hope, a little bit dignified,
إنه، آمل، وقور بعض الشيء،
but mostly rather vulgar. (Laughter)
ولكنه في الغالب بذيء. (ضحك)
And energetic, I hope, too.
وحيوي، آمل ذلك أيضًا.
I let him into my life because the Sèvres pink elephant vase allowed me to do so.
تركته يدخل حياتي لأن مزهرية الفيل الوردي السيفرس سمحت لي بفعل ذلك.
And before that Leonardo,
وقبل ليوناردو،
I understood that this object could become part of a journey for me every day,
فهمت أن هذا التمثال يمكن أن يصبح جزءً من رحلة بالنسبة لي كل يوم،
sitting in my office.
يجلس في مكتبي.
I really hope that others, all of you,
أنا آمل حقًا أن الآخرين، كلكم،
visiting objects in the museum,
من تزورون التماثيل في المتحف،
and taking them home and finding them for yourselves,
وتأخذونها إلى المنزل وتجدونها من أجل أنفسكم،
will allow those objects to flourish in your imaginative lives.
أن تسمحوا لهذه التماثيل بأن تزدهر في حياتكم الإبداعية.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)